Okay, so maybe you got a little lost in
that hairy code in the last video, and
that is totally okay and totally
expected at this point in time. Um, so
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
show you a co tool that will help you
walk through code so that you don't get
lost in the future. And if you do get
lost, you can use it to walk through and
help you understand it. It's also great
for finding bugs. Um, and that is the
Safari debugger. So I have here fired up
in live server in Safari, um, the app
that we just wrote. So, we'll put in uh
four A's. And you can see it gave us our
GPA and the message. So, if you want to
use the debugging tool, um you'll hit
command option I and that will pop up
this little window at the bottom, which
is the Safari developer tools. The tab
you want to you're going to want to
click on is the sources tab. If you
click on that, you'll see some very
familiar code, at least hopefully,
because this is the code you just wrote.
Um,
so what I'm going to do is I am going to
click on line 16. When I click on line
16, you'll notice it puts this gray
highlight. What that is is that is a
break point. A break point says pause
the code execution and give me control
because I want to control how this
executes and I want to go line by line.
So what it's going to do is it's going
to run the code all the way up till line
16. Then it's going to pause and then
it's going to let you take over. So I'm
going to reload this page to trigger the
code. So the code is running and it has
paused. Um
and so we can see here that counter is
going to be set to zero. It over here
there are the controls for the debugger.
Our code has paused. Nothing is
happening. You'll notice our page is
partially loaded but not fully loaded.
That's because we've paused everything.
So if we run this line, the highlighted
portion will run next. You'll notice
this let counter equals zero is darkly
highlighted. That's because that is the
portion that's going to run when we hit
the next button. So there are two next
buttons. There's the step over button
and the step into button. I typically
use the step into button. Um and when we
talk about functions, I'll explain the
difference later, but for now just click
the step into button or click F7 or
command semicolon. So that will run the
very next line of code. So we've run
that line of code and now over here we
can see we have a new variable called
counter which has a value of zero
if we hit the step into button again. So
right now it's going to see if zero is
less than four. It is. So we should
expect this loop to start. So we'll hit
next. And now we're in the loop. If
counter if we hover over it counter is
zero. Counter + one would be one. So we
should expect this prompt to say what is
your letter grade for class one. If we
hit next, it runs this line of code and
says, "What is your letter grade for
class one?" We're going to put a B+ for
now. So, we hit okay. And now, if we
hover over letter grade, we can see that
letter grade is B+. We have another
variable called GPA. And it's undefined
because we haven't run this line of code
yet. When we run line 19, GPA will go
from being undefined to being zero. So,
we'll hit next. And now we have a GPA of
zero and a letter grade of B+. Now we've
come to our if statement.
We're going to see if B+ is equal to A.
Because it's not, we should expect it to
jump to line 24 and check if it's equal
to A minus. If we hit next, sure enough,
there it is. And now we're checking if
B+ is equal to A minus. It's not. So, we
should expect it to skip over line 25
and 26 and jump to line 27 to see if B+
is equal to B+. If we hit next, it does.
Now we're seeing if B+ is B+. It is. So
we should expect it to enter line 28 and
compare and then execute that line. And
then it should finish that. Hit this
closing curly brace on line 29 and jump
all the way down
um to line 57 at the end of the if
statement because this is where the if
statement ends. So we're going to hit
that next button. We'll hit next. Sure
enough, B+ is the same as B+. So, we're
going to set GPA to 3.3. Right now, GPA
is zero. We hit the next button. Now,
our GPA is 3.3. And then it jumped to
the end of the if statement. Our total
GPA, we started off at zero. But we're
going to say set it equal to zero plus
whatever is in GPA. And so, if we run
that line
now, if we hover over total GPA, it's
3.3.
And you can see the highlighted line is
this counter plus+. So our counter
variable is zero. I told you plus+
increments. So if we run this next line
of code, we should see that our counter
goes from 0 to 1. So we'll hit the next
button. And so now our counter is 1. Now
we're checking if 1 is less than four.
It is. So we're going to start the loop.
And then 1 + 1 is two. So we should
expect to see what is your letter grade
for class 2. If we run that, we get a
prompt. What is your letter grade for
class 2? And I will say A. So you can
see how quickly an if statement can run.
And our letter grade is A. Our GPA is
undefined. If we hit next, now our GPA
is zero. And don't mix up GPA with total
GPA. Our total GPA is 3.3.
So if we hit the next button, um, we get
that our GPA is 4.0. And it drops
immediately to the end of the if
statement. It didn't even check any of
the other conditions cuz as soon as it
found the condition that was true, it
did that and then skipped to the end. So
now our total GPA is 3.3 and we're going
to add on an A here. So it should be
like uh 7.3. If we hit next, our total
GPA is 7.3. At this point, we've run our
loop twice. We've evaluated it and we
know that this loop works. So maybe
you're done testing it and there's
another portion of the code that you
want to test. Like for example, this if
statement we want to and maybe this
total GPA calculation, we want to make
sure that actually works. So what you
can do is you can add a breakpoint to
line 61 and come up and remove the
breakpoint by clicking on it on line 16.
Now you can hit this uh it looks like a
mix between the pause and the play
button and that will continue script
execution and it will run all the way up
until it hits your next breakpoint. So,
we'll continue to the next one. And it
says, "What is your letter grade for
class three?" We'll put in a C minus.
And then, what is your letter grade for
class 4? We'll give ourselves another A.
But you'll notice it didn't pause
between loops. It just immediately went
through the code twice without any
pause. Now, it has paused again because
it's hit our break point on line 61. Our
total GPA is 13, but that's not actually
our GPA because a grade point average um
is your grade points divided by the
total number of classes you've taken to
get an average. And so we've taken four
classes, so we're going to take 13 and
divide it by four. We'll hit next. And
our GPA is 3.25.
So now I'm going to show you something
you can do with the debugger and it's
called forcing a condition. So right
here, maybe we want to test this if
statement and we really want to test
what happens when we pass in exactly 3.3
is the GPA at um
and maybe you don't want to figure out
the letter grades that would be
necessary to get a 3.3. Um so what you
can do is called forcing a condition.
Right now our GPA evaluates to 3.25 and
that's not going to work for us. So,
what we're going to do is we're going to
click over to the console tab and we're
going to say total GPA equals 3.3 and
then we'll hit enter. As soon as we have
done that, we'll go over to our sources
tab and hover over GPA. And now, even
though it was 3.25, that's what all of
our calculations came out to, we've
forced it to be something else. So, now
we can check if this if statement works
the way it's supposed to. If you have a
GPA of exactly 3.3, then you should get
this first message. So, now we've forced
the GPA to be what we want it to be. Um,
so if total GPA 3.3 is greater than or
equal to 3.3, 3.3 and 3.3 are equal, so
we should expect this next alert
function to run. If we hit the next
button, sure enough, it drops to that
alert statement. And if we hit the next
button, it says, "Your GPA is 3.3. Great
job. Your consistent effort is paying
off." And then the whole rest of that
message. So using the console, we can
force a certain condition to be met so
that we can test specific portions of
our code even if the prior calculations
didn't allow it. So, we'll hit close and
then it drops to the end of the script
tag. If you were just running this
normally um and not running it using
live server, then you might not have
this extra code because we're running it
using live server. There's some extra
code here. It's just JavaScript to make
it so that your window reloads if
something changes, things like that. And
so, it's just their extra code. You can
totally ignore it. Um but in order for
your page to fully load, you'll see it's
still in the partial loading. You'll
need to hit this continue button one
more time and then boom, your page is
loaded.